[music]
>> All right. Hello everyone. So, I'm going
to be talking about how when you're
making your MCV servers, how you can
improve your tool schemas to make them
more reliable when agents use it.
And my name is Pamela Fox and I'm
currently at Microsoft or GitHub,
whichever one you like the most. I
apparently work for both companies now
because we got reorged a couple weeks
ago. So, yay.
Now, since this is a you know, that's
like a very you know, serious sounding
talk title, but let's start off with
something more fun. So, the question is
can we use MCP
to design our outfits, right? Which is
like very important to be able to do.
So, here I've got
VS code open. It says, oh, I'm
presenting at PiAI about MCP. Do I have
any MCP clothing, right? So, it does a
little search, right? So, it searched
for, you know, it even knows it expands
MCP model context particle theme
clothing. It found back a bunch of image
results. So, you can send back binary
from the MCV server. It says, yes, you
do have an MCP theme dress. You down
with MCP, yeah, you know me. As it it
shows me it and this is an MCV app. So,
we can render an MCV app to show as like
a little gallery. I'm like, okay, great.
Love the pink. Matches Pydantic AI. Can
we get some accessories? Like, okay, you
got this, you got this. Okay, it's
looking good. And I said, all right, I
also need a jacket. It was like, all
right, and now show me my complete
outfit. We got the dress, the jacket and
the earrings. Boom. All right, so that's
kind of a fun thing that you can do with
MCP and also shows the fact that MCP
servers, they can return more than just
text. They can return images, binary and
they can return apps. So, you can have
these you know, like actual
interactivity there and you can start
thinking about what more you can build
in MCP. Now, this will fill up your
context window quite quickly
if you start doing a lot of searches in
your closet depending on how many
options you have. But it's it's pretty
fun.
Okay. So, going back to what we're
actually going to do. So, first let's
build a you know, just basic MCV server
with Python. What does it look like?
Here is a fast MCV server.
You know, we've got this is for adding
expenses to a database. So, we've got a
date, we have an amount, we have a
category and we do description. Most of
these are strings except for the amount
which is a float. And so, what happens
is that those tool parameters, they
become a JSON schema. So, fast MCV
automatically turns that into a schema
and then sends that down to the LLMs and
that's what the LLMs see and how they
decide what they're going to do with it,
right?
And a lot of times that's what I see
people start off with when they're
building these servers is these kind of
like bare bare types, right? Now, the
thing is you know, most of the things
are strings. So, if you you know, if you
tell it like, oh, you can just put any
sort of string in there, right? So, here
if I say like, okay, I bought a $12
chocolate bar yesterday, dandelion and I
give it to that server, it's just going
to you know, it's going to say, all
right, this is what I think the date
should look like. This is what I think
the category should be, description,
right? So, the LLM's going to decide how
to fill in those arguments.
And without any constraints, it can be
very very creative, right? So, this is
for category. I ran it 83 times to see
what it would come up with, multiple
languages, Spanish, whatever.
And we got a wide wide range of
categories, right? And you know, that
can be good, but a lot of times you do
want to you know, rein your LLMs in. You
want to constrain the schema more to
have more predictability in the way your
tools are getting called.
So, there's many ways that you can
constrain the arguments when you're
building these fast MCV servers. The
first thing that I have to like beg
everyone to do is add a description to
your fields, right? So, instead of just
saying it's a string, you say annotated
string field, you give it a description
and you say, hey, this is a string.
Here's the description of this. Now, you
understand what this argument is, right?
Because otherwise, it literally is only
going to see the name and the type and
that is not enough information. So, you
have to have to add a description,
right? So,
start off with that and so then that
description gets added to the schema.
The next thing we could do is we can
actually constrain types, right? We
could use a literal type from Python. We
could say, hey, this thing can only be
one of these you know, these types here,
right? And so, that then becomes this
list in the JSON schema and so, the LLM
sees, oh, okay, I'm only allowed to do
that. And best if you do both, right?
You say, hey, here's exactly the types
you're allowed to choose and here is
your thinking process you should use
when trying to decide which of these
types you're going to use.
So, those are some options.
So, here's a question. This is I tried
to do this as like a this is like a
research talk. I'm not a researcher, but
I cosplay.
So, do agents actually like stricter
schemas, right? I my theory, my
hypothesis is that they would and that's
how I wrote my abstract.
But I have to evaluate and actually find
out, right? So, I set up a Pydantic AI
agent and pointed it at my MCV server.
And I was like, okay, you're going to
help users log expenses and here's
today's date, right?
And then I wrote all these different
tools with different schemas. So, all
the schemas I showed you, I wrote tools
with all those different variants. And
then in the agent code, I can just
filter it down and say, hey agent,
you're only allowed to see these
variants right now. So, that way I could
make some matches and see, okay, the
agent with these variants, what does it
decide to do, right?
And then I set up a bunch of
evaluations. Now, the funny thing is I
thought I used Pydantic AI evals for
these evaluations cuz I totally asked
Copilot to do that in my plan and then I
was looking at it yesterday and I was
like, oh my god, it just wrote its own
evaluation framework. So, that happens
and like that works too, right? That's
fine, right?
So, so yeah, it it just came up with an
evaluation framework that looks similar
to Pydantic AI evals.
But basically, I just set up all these
cases and say, hey, you know, this is
the prompt. This is the category I
expect. This is the date I expect and
here's the amount, right?
So, you know, it came up with lots of
different variations, different
languages, etc. to you know, try and
trick it.
Then I've run all the evals with a
certain model. I set the seed for the
models that supported for better
reproducibility. I set the temperature
to zero here to make it less creative
and then you know, output all those
results in some JSON and also markdown
and then I ended up just working with a
coding agent to say, hey, all right,
here's my results. Can you help me just
muddle through them? Cuz even with a
human readable report, I got tired of
reading those reports. I was like, can
you just can you just look at the
report? Like this is like the 10th
report I've seen and and that was
helpful for me.
All right. So, I ran the schemas. So, we
I compared
the you know, having a string with a
description, having a literal, having an
enum and then having the enum with the
description. So, I looked at was the
tool called at all? Cuz I think that's
interesting that happens a lot is that
it may not it doesn't feel like it has
enough information to even call the tool
and it like asked the clarifying
question. Says like, I you know, I I I I
I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I
I I I I I don't feel empowered enough to
make this decision.
So, that's you know, the first row is
was the tool called at all? You can see
with the just a description, it was only
15 out of 17 times. And then when it was
called, did the category match the one
we expected in our ground truth? So, I
set up all this ground truth and said,
hey, for this prompt, I expect this
category, right? And then I also looked
at how big the schema is cuz everything
is about tradeoffs and the more you add
to your schema, the more constraints you
add, the longer description, uh
so for example, you can see
this question here. The day after
tomorrow, I will buy a bus pass for $20.
With only the description, the agent
says, hey, could you please specify the
category? It just didn't know. Once we
had both the enum and the description,
it was like, okay, cool, transit and
fuel. So, we kind of like by adding by
doing the enum, it basically forced the
LLM to be like, okay, well, they really
really want me to pick one of these
categories. I'm going to do it. That's
what it seemed to like empower it.
And then when did category match
improve, right? So, you know, we can say
like, okay, I paid 99 for an app. When
we had a literal, it became apparel and
beauty, which is funny. App apparel, I
guess.
And then when we gave it more
description, then we got you know,
correct electronics and tech. So, it's
interesting to see when you run these
evals like the kind of failures you see
and and what things get better when you
do. So, what you generally see is that
yeah, as we added both the description
and an enum, we did get what looked like
you know, much better results. We also
had a much bigger schema size. So, you
do need a like keep that you know,
tradeoff in mind.
But it looks like evals are better.
Now, I wanted to look at one more
schema variant here. So, the date date
field. Now, I thought date was
interesting because I set it as a
string.
I could also do a string with a
description. I could do an actual Python
date type and that becomes
a format date in the JSON schema. And
you can specify regex patterns. It's
another way you could do it. So, any any
of your MCV like
arguments, the tools could actually be
defined as a regex and you can tell the
LLM like, hey, your answer has to match
this regex. It's always a fun to try and
get LLMs to adhere to regexes, right?
>> [snorts]
[laughter]
>> So, that's what I decided to try.
And
the thing that was fascinating is that I
got the same results across every single
schema including the one that didn't
even have a description. So, I didn't
even tell it that I wanted it to be in
year month day format and every single
time it gave it back as year month day
format because that's the ISO 8601 or
whatever, right? So,
without even a description. And this is
like it infuriated me so much cuz I'm
like, no, the whole point of my talk is
to show people that you should have
stricter schemas cuz you're going to get
way better results. But then I ran the
evaluations and was like, "Okay, well,
as it turns out, LLMs are really good at
just assuming that if something is
called date, that you want it in like
standard date format, and they will just
give that to you, right?"
Um now it was still interesting to see
the places where they failed cuz they
all failed at the same thing. And these
were still interesting, right? Cuz I was
running these right around uh February
28th, and there's no February 29th this
year, but only some of the models know
that, and this model This is GPT-4 1
mini. GPT-4 1 mini couldn't work out the
fact that there is no uh leap year this
year. So it kept saying, you know,
February 29th. I'm like, "Uh-uh, that
that doesn't exist, right?" Uh so it is
always really interesting to see the
ways in you know, in which you know,
your LLMs will fail to call tools. In
this case, the schema made no
difference. I still learned interesting
things about the way kind of mishandled
date calculation and and made up dates
that didn't exist. Uh but yeah, the
schema, you know, didn't make a
difference. However, it does make a
difference for your code, right? It's
nice in Python when we can use types cuz
we can use them in other places, too,
and be like, "Okay, this is the type we
expected."
All right, so then I wanted to run some
more evals, right? So one question is
like, "Okay, that was all with GPT-4 1
mini. You know, we've all moved on past
mini. We're over it. Do all models think
alike? What if I run it with others?" So
I did it with 40, 41 mini, and 53 codex.
I even did it with 54 a couple days ago,
too. Uh 54 is quite good. Um so you
know, so then I looked at the stats, and
you know, generally um what we see like
uh is interesting. It's actually
different across the both of them. So
for category, category match got worse
for 53 codex uh in terms of matching my
ground truth. It just disagreed with my
ground truth. And maybe 53 codex is just
smarter than me, and I should just
change my ground truth to match what
codex thinks.
Um but then with 53 codex, the date
match there really improved. And that's
where is because 53 codex is just better
at uh we'll say math. Um
not that LLMs can do math, but
uh it didn't make the mistakes with
like, you know, mistakenly doing New
Year and like how to calculate 2 Mondays
ago and stuff like that.
Uh so So that was pretty interesting to
see is that, you know, for something
like date calculation, we do see much
better with the new models. For
something that's a little more like
wishy-washy like, "Okay, what category
is this?" Sometimes these newer
reasoning models will disagree with you
and uh you know, come up with something
else.
So you can see some you know, examples
here like yeah, a spa treatment. Is that
health and fitness or apparel and
beauty? You know, maybe that's just too
ambiguous, right? So sometimes when you
run evals, you look at the results and
be like, "You know what? Maybe maybe I
should change my you know, the data I'm
running it with. Like maybe this date
like maybe this date is actually
ambiguous, and I should be changing it
anyway."
Um because it's just it's too hard even
for a human to decide, right? Like maybe
some of you think that you know, maybe
some of you agree with the failures here
and and think that those are the right
answers. Uh so it's it's just all Every
time you run evals, you you know, learn
something.
Now I wanted to try the reasoning models
on different reasoning levels cuz
whenever we they come up with reasoning
models and they're like, "Oh, okay." And
you're like, "Great. What level do I use
it at, right? Do I use it at low,
medium, high, extra high, right?" And
you'll people people on Twitter is like,
"Oh, you've got to code with 53 extra
high. It's the best." Like, "Okay, I'll
try." Um
>> [laughter]
>> So uh so that's what I did. So I I
looked at 53 codex from low to extra
high. And as you can see, it did the
best on low in terms of my category
match heuristic, right? And once again,
just as soon as it started thinking
about things, it started like
overthinking to the point of disagreeing
with what I had put there, right? Um and
you know, once again, maybe maybe some
of that overthinking like, you know,
actually you know, maybe it was thinking
even better than me, and so I could go
back and and look.
Um but there's definitely an effect that
the reasoning has on the selection
process.
Uh so it is it is worth looking at what
happens when you give these models the
ability to think more. And of course,
the latency goes way up, right? From
7,000 up to 12,000 milliseconds. And uh
that's always a thing you have to think
about when you're deciding whether to do
reasoning.
Okay, so next I was like, "All right, so
we looked at models. What about agent
frameworks?" Everyone's trying to decide
what agent framework to use. There's so
many of them, right? Uh developers are
constantly asking me that, right?
Obviously, since we're at the PyAI
conference, I'll tell them to use
Pydantic AI, but you know, at each
conference, I'll just give a different
answer, whoever pays me.
Uh [clears throat] so also it since I
said I you know, I
work for my
Microsoft GitHub now, my GitHub,
whatever.
Uh so I did use the GitHub Copilot SDK.
So I set up a Copilot SDK agent um with
the server and uh you know, to try and
So same prompt, same server, and the
only thing that's different is whatever
agentic loop is inside this agent
framework, right? And they do have some
subtle differences in the agentic loops
sometimes.
Um you know, that that can affect these
things.
Uh and so then I looked at the
comparisons, and as you can see,
actually they got the exactly same
numbers. So uh they have either really
similar agentic loops, which is very
possible cuz basically what is an agent?
It's tool calling in a loop. Uh
or
you're yeah, like it you know, this is
just a fairly deterministic thing.
Actually, I have to say, I did have to
rerun these numbers. Okay, there was I'm
like making Copilot look good here
because originally it failed on almost
all of the date cases because I ran the
eval first at 9:00 p.m. Pacific time,
and it got every date off by one.
And I don't know why because in my
prompt, I told it what time it was on my
machine. I think that there's some
um because GitHub Copilot kind of has
its own system prompt, too. I think
there might be a system prompt like
inside that agent runtime that has uh a
UTC time instead of So So I got Luckily,
I woke up at 3:00 a.m. Um and reran the
evals, and and that time, you know, it
worked because we were the same day as
UTC. Um so interesting things happen
with with date and time.
Uh okay, so So there we go. So some
conclusions here. I originally thought
the conclusion was going to be that
structured schemas definitely make
agents more reliable. And a year ago,
I think that would have been true cuz I
This was all based off of errors I was
seeing originally with uh MCP servers
that didn't have structured schemas and
like would just LLMs weren't doing good
call time calling them. But now the LLMs
are so good that they've they've you
know, that
it doesn't really matter that much as
long as you give it enough of an idea of
what you're looking for. But there's
still a lot of benefit to structured
schemas. We did see slight improvements
in agent reliability, but it just means
like you have more type-safe code,
right? And you know, you're able to
better reason about your code. You get
better validation, IDE auto-completion,
you know, fewer runtime errors, right?
So even if the structured schemas, you
know, don't actually improve the agent
reliability, I think it's often worth it
to do it.
Uh but of course,
uh
the only way to know is to do evals as
um as Miles says, I have your 20 tier.
>> [laughter]
>> Um and uh and he's got the hats for it,
too.
So you don't really know these things
unless you unless you do the evals. And
and every time that I do evals, like I I
you know, learn something new and
interesting uh you know, about the
system that I'm
that I'm evaluating.
All right, so uh thank you every Oh, I'm
supposed to plug Logfire. Okay, yeah.
Here you go. We're We're going to plug
everything, right? So we got Pydantic
AI. Okay, so yeah, when you do Logfire,
it's pretty cool. Like so I've got
Logfire instrumenting both the agents
and and the tools, right? So it'll be
like,
I I bought $20 of chocolate today at
Dandelion. I do recommend Dandelion
chocolate in San Francisco. It's so
good. All right, so then that should
send a call out to
our MCP server, which is running over
here. Here we go. There we go. Is that
That's earlier today? Let's see.
Reasoning. It's got to reason about it.
Yeah, it There we go. Reasoning. All
right, it's running running running, and
then we're going to
do this last 5 minutes. Logfire is
really cool. I don't know how many of
you have used Logfire?
All right, nice. It's it's really nice
UI. I quite enjoy using it. Uh so there
we go. So we can see we got a tool call
request, right? So you can instrument
your MCP servers in like four lines of
code, instrument the agent servers, um
and then with the Logfire traces, then
you know, you can
um you know, also just point uh you
know, evals at your traces, too, and
learn from them as well.
Okay, great. Plugged all the things. Uh
so you can grab my slides from here and
the code from here, and uh and I'm happy
to answer any questions. Thank you,
everyone.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you. Um I'm glad to know that I
can use my FSA for spa if I use a low
thinking model. This is great. Um we
have time for one question.
Uh when have you seen uh schemas and uh
strict validation making things worse?
Right. So also, the thing I didn't
mention is that um some of these schemas
originally completely broke models. So,
remember that enum I was showing,
originally enum if you did an enum in
FastMCP,
FastMCP serialized it using this
particular thing called like JSON schema
references, and the Opus models hated
it. They just would the API would error.
And so, I like reported in the FastMCP
tracker and like they were kind of
trying to decide what to do cuz on the
one hand, they were outputting valid
JSON schema according to the JSON schema
spec. On the other hand, some models
apparently like weren't fully compliant
with the spec. So, Jeremiah ended up
changing it to basically
inline those those enums. And basically,
the reason enums and literals come out
exactly the same is because he made it
so that when you do an enum, it ends up
being like this cuz it's actually
technically supposed to use this like
whole references thing, but it's kind of
like pointers in your schema, and the
models were not handling those pointers.
So, that's like a plug for FastMCP. If
you do use FastMCP, like every time I've
had an MCP tool like issue
compatibility, I've reported it, and a
lot of times that means simplifying the
schemas to work better across models and
across clients cuz I saw there was a VS
code issue, too, that they improved. And
that's also what I like I talked to the
folks behind the GitHub MCP server, and
they've also had issues with JSON schema
where they're like, "Oh, like models
don't like if you have like this empty
object, right?" So,
so yeah, I So, none of my examples today
actually broke the models because
FastMCP is like kind of battle-hardened
now, and you know, people have tried it
with so many different models and
clients.
Awesome. Thank you.
>> [music]
[applause]